Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Papers, General and Literary Manuscripts, Wilson Library, The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in the Walt Whitman Papers, General and Literary Manuscripts, Wilson Library, The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill
12010
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry Manuscripts prose
Walt Whitman Papers, General and Literary Manuscripts Wilson Library University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Chapel Hill, NC 27514-8890
This catalog was created from digital images of the original manuscripts and from cataloguing information obtained by the Walt Whitman Archive from the Manuscripts Department, Wilson Library, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, where the original manuscripts are held.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with repository.
Scope and Content
The Walt Whitman Papers at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill contains ten poetry manuscripts, three galley proofs, four prose manuscript fragments, one manuscript note to the printer, and a first-edition copy of November Boughs, inscribed by Thomas B. Harned. This catalog contains descriptions of only those items deemed poetry and/or prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- [Land of the potent-large!], undated; unc.00001; xxx.00501; xxx.00267; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 1)
  This manuscript includes a fragment of a poem, approximately seven lines, that is possibly from an early draft of As a Strong Bird on Pinions Free, a poem Whitman originally wrote for the June 1872 Dartmouth College commencement exercises. This poem was later revised and published as Thou Mother with Thy Equal Brood, Leaves of Grass ( 1881–1882 ).
- Paumanok, about 1888; unc.00002; xxx.00312; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 3)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, Paumanok, which was first published in the New York Herald on February 29, 1888. Reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ).
- A font of type, about 1888; unc.00003; xxx.00317; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 5)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, A Font of Type, which was first published in November Boughs in 1888.
- My Canary Bird, about 1888; unc.00004; xxx.00319; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 6)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, My Canary Bird, which was first published in the New York Herald on March 2, 1888. Reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ).
- Out of May's shows selected, about 1888; unc.00005; xxx.00328; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 7)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, Out of May's Shows Selected, which was first published in the New York Herald on May 10, 1888. Reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ).
- With husky-haughty lips, O sea, about 1884; unc.00010; xxx.00340; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 8)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, With Husky-Haughty Lips, O Sea!, which was first published in Harper's Monthly in March 1884. Reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ).
- True Conquerors, about 1888; unc.00006; xxx.00354; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 9)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, True Conquerors, which was first published in the New York Herald on February 15, 1888. Revised and reprinted in the "Sands at Seventy" annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- The United States to Old World Critics, about 1888; unc.00007; xxx.00355; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 10)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, The United States to Old World Critics, which was first published in the New York Herald on May 8, 1888. Reprinted in the "Sands at Seventy" annex to Leaves of Grass (1888).
- While not the past forgetting, about 1888; unc.00008; xxx.00361; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 11)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, While Not the Past Forgetting. Whitman claimed that the poem was published on May 30, 1888, though no copy of such a version has yet been located. The poem was published in November Boughs in 1888.
- an evening lull, about 1888; unc.00009; xxx.00374; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Folder 13)
  This is a manuscript draft of the poem, "An Evening Lull," which was first published in November Boughs in 1888.
- [for Elias Hicks], 1883-1888; unc.00011; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Folder 11)
  This manuscript contains a passage that would appear within the essay Notes (Such as They Are) Founded on Elias Hicks in November Boughs in 1888.
- Then my mother hastening, 1883-1888; unc.00012; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Folder 17)
  This manuscript contains a passage that would appear in Notes (Such as They Are) Founded on Elias Hicks in November Boughs in 1888, which was a prefatory note for the essay Elias Hicks.
- The two songs on this page are, June 19, 1888; unc.00014; xxx.00373; xxx.00374; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Folder 14)
  This manuscript contains the footnote for poems Now Precedent Songs, Farewell and An Evening Lull, first published in Sands at Seventy, an annex of November Boughs in 1888. According to Horace Traubel, the footnote was written by Whitman on 19 June 1888 (With Walt Whitman in Camden [Boston: Small, Maynard, 1906] 1:353).